<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../documentation/schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<story>
    <title>THE OPEN DOOR</title>
   
<chapter n="1">
    THE OPEN DOOR.
    
    <p tone="n/a"><year>1881</year></p>
    
<p tone="happiness"> 
<place>Brentwood</place> stands on that fine and wealthy slope of country—one of the richest in <place>Scotland</place>—which lies between the <place>Pentland Hills</place> and the <place>Firth</place>. In clear weather you could see the blue gleam—like a bent bow, embracing the wealthy fields and scattered houses—of the great <place>estuary</place> on one side of you, and on the other the blue heights, not gigantic like those we had been used to, but just high enough for all the glories of the atmosphere, the play of clouds, and sweet reflections, which give to a hilly country an interest and a charm which nothing else can emulate. <place>Edinburgh</place>—with its two lesser heights, the <place>Castle</place> and the <place>Calton Hill</place>, its spires and towers piercing through the smoke, and <place>Arthur’s Seat</place> lying crouched behind, like a guardian no longer very needful, taking his repose beside the well-beloved charge, which is now, so to speak, able to take care of itself without him—lay at our right hand. From the lawn and drawing-room windows we could see all these varieties of landscape. The color was sometimes a little chilly, but sometimes, also, as animated and full of vicissitude as a drama. I was never tired of it. Its color and freshness revived the eyes which had grown weary of arid plains and blazing skies. It was always cheery, and fresh, and full of repose.
</p>
<p tone="serious">
The summer was a very happy period of repose for us all. The warmth of <place>Indian</place> suns was still in our veins. It seemed to us that we could never have enough of the greenness, the dewiness, the freshness of the northern landscape. Even its mists were pleasant to us, taking all the fever out of us, and pouring in vigor and refreshment. In autumn we followed the fashion of the time, and went away for change which we did not in the least require. It was when the family had settled down for the winter, when the days were short and dark, and the rigorous reign of frost upon us, that the incidents occurred which alone could justify me in intruding upon the world my private affairs. These incidents were, however, of so curious a character, that I hope my inevitable references to my own family and pressing personal interests will meet with a general pardon.
</p>
    <p tone="fear">
But I was confident in my home-comfort and peacefulness. When I got back to my <place>club</place>, however, three or four letters were lying for one, upon some of which I noticed the <quote>“immediate,”</quote> <quote>“urgent,”</quote> which old-fashioned people and anxious people still believe will influence the post-office and quicken the speed of the mails. I was about to open one of these, when the <place>club</place> porter brought me two telegrams, one of which, he said, had arrived the night before. I opened, as was to be expected, the last first, and this was what I read: <quote>“Why don’t you come or answer? For God’s sake, come. He is much worse.”</quote> This was a thunderbolt to fall upon a man’s head who had one only son, and he the light of his eyes! The other telegram, which I opened with hands trembling so much that I lost time by my haste, was to much the same purport: <quote>“No better; <character ref="Simson">doctor</character> afraid of brain-fever. Calls for you day and night. Let nothing detain you.”</quote> The first thing I did was to look up the time-tables to see if there was any way of getting off sooner than by the night-train, though I knew well enough there was not; and then I read the letters, which furnished, alas! too clearly, all the details. They told me that the boy had been pale for some time, with a scared look. His <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> had noticed it before I left home, but would not say anything to alarm me. This look had increased day by day: and soon it was observed that <character ref="Roland">Roland</character> came home at a wild gallop through the park, his pony panting and in foam, himself <quote>“as white as a sheet,”</quote> but with the perspiration streaming from his forehead. For a long time he had resisted all questioning, but at length had developed such strange changes of mood, showing a reluctance to go to school, a desire to be fetched in the carriage at night,—which was a ridiculous piece of luxury,—an unwillingness to go out into the grounds, and nervous start at every sound, that his <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> had insisted upon an explanation. When the boy—our boy <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, who had never known what fear was—began to talk to her of voices he had heard in the park, and shadows that had appeared to him among the ruins, my wife promptly put him to bed and sent for <character ref="Dr. Simson">Dr. Simson</character>, which, of course, was the only thing to do.
    </p>
    <p tone="sadness">
        I looked at him from the door of his room, for we were afraid to go near, lest we should disturb that blessed sleep. It looked like actual sleep, not the lethargy into which my wife told me he would sometimes fall. She told me everything in the next room, which communicated with his, rising now and then and going to the door of communication; and in this there was much that was very startling and confusing to the mind. It appeared that ever since the winter began—since it was early dark, and night had fallen before his return from school—he had been hearing voices among the ruins: at first only a groaning, he said, at which his pony was as much alarmed as he was, but by degrees a voice. The tears ran down my wife’s cheeks as she described to me how he would start up in the night and cry out, <quote>“Oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in! oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in!”</quote> with a pathos which rent her heart. And she sitting there all the time, only longing to do everything his heart could desire! But though she would try to soothe him, crying, <quote>“You are at home, my darling. I am here. Don’t you know me? Your <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> is here!”</quote> he would only stare at her, and after a while spring up again with the same cry. At other times he would be quite reasonable, she said, asking eagerly when I was coming, but declaring that he must go with me as soon as I did so, <quote>“to let them in.”</quote> <quote>“The <character ref="Simson">doctor</character> thinks his nervous system must have received a shock,”</quote> my wife said. <quote>“Oh, <character ref="Henry">Henry</character>, can it be that we have pushed him on too much with his work—a delicate boy like <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>? And what is his work in comparison with his health? Even you would think little of honors or prizes if it hurt the boy’s health.”</quote> Even I!—as if I were an inhuman <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character> sacrificing my child to my ambition. But I would not increase her trouble by taking any notice. After awhile they persuaded me to lie down, to rest, and to eat, none of which things had been possible since I received their letters. The mere fact of being on the spot, of course, in itself was a great thing; and when I knew that I could be called in a moment, as soon as he was awake and wanted me, I felt capable, even in the dark, chill morning twilight, to snatch an hour or two’s sleep. As it happened, I was so worn out with the strain of anxiety, and he so quieted and consoled by knowing I had come, that I was not disturbed till the afternoon, when the twilight had again settled down. There was just daylight enough to see his face when I went to him; and what a change in a fortnight! He was paler and more worn, I thought, than even in those dreadful days in the plains before we left <place>India</place>. His hair seemed to me to have grown long and lank; his eyes were like blazing lights projecting out of his white face. He got hold of my hand in a cold and tremulous clutch, and waved to everybody to go away. <quote>“Go away—even <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>,”</quote> he said; <quote>“go away.”</quote> This went to her heart; for she did not like that even I should have more of the boy’s confidence than herself; but my wife has never been a woman to think of herself, and she left us alone. <quote>“Are they all gone?”</quote> he said eagerly. <quote>“They would not let me speak. The <character ref="Simson">doctor</character> treated me as if I were a fool. You know I am not a fool, <character ref="Mortimer">papa</character>.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Yes, yes, my boy, I know. But you are ill, and quiet is so necessary. You are not only not a fool, <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, but you are reasonable and understand. When you are ill you must deny yourself; you must not do everything that you might do being well.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious">He waved his thin hand with a sort of indignation. <quote>“Then, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>, I am not ill,”</quote> he cried. <quote>“Oh, I thought when you came you would not stop me,—you would see the sense of it! What do you think is the matter with me, all of you? <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> is well enough; but he is only a <character ref="Simson">doctor</character>. What do you think is the matter with me? I am no more ill than you are. A <character ref="Simson">doctor</character>, of course, he thinks you are ill the moment he looks at you—that’s what he’s there for—and claps you into bed.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Which is the best place for you at present, my dear boy.”</quote></p>

<p tone="suspenseful"><quote>“I made up my mind,”</quote> cried the little fellow, <quote>“that I would stand it till you came home. I said to myself, I won’t frighten <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> and the girls. But now, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>,”</quote> he cried, half jumping out of bed, <quote>“it’s not illness: it’s a secret.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious">His eyes shone so wildly, his face was so swept with strong feeling, that my heart sank within me. It could be nothing but fever that did it, and fever had been so fatal. I got him into my arms to put him back into bed. <quote>“<character ref="Roland">Roland</character>,”</quote> I said, humoring the poor child, which I knew was the only way, <quote>“if you are going to tell me this secret to do any good, you know you must be quite quiet, and not excite yourself. If you excite yourself, I must not let you speak.”</quote></p>

<p tone="sadness"><quote>“Yes, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>,”</quote> said the boy. He was quiet directly, like a man, as if he quite understood. When I had laid him back on his pillow, he looked up at me with that grateful, sweet look with which children, when they are ill, break one’s heart, the water coming into his eyes in his weakness. <quote>“I was sure as soon as you were here you would know what to do,”</quote> he said.</p>

<p tone="sadness"><quote>“To be sure, my boy. Now keep quiet, and tell it all out like a man.”</quote> To think I was telling lies to my own child! for I did it only to humor him, thinking, poor little fellow, his brain was wrong.</p>

<p tone="suspenseful"><quote>“Yes, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>. <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>, there is some one in the park—some one that has been badly used.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Hush, my dear; you remember there is to be no excitement. Well, who is this somebody, and who has been ill-using him? We will soon put a stop to that.”</quote></p>

<p tone="suspenseful"><quote>“All,”</quote> cried <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, <quote>“but it is not so easy as you think. I don’t know who it is. It is just a cry. Oh, if you could hear it! It gets into my head in my sleep. I heard it as clear—as clear; and they think that I am dreaming, or raving perhaps,”</quote> the boy said, with a sort of disdainful smile.
    </p>
    <p tone="suspenseful">
<quote>“Dreamed?—that!”</quote> He was springing up again when he suddenly bethought himself, and lay down flat, with the same sort of smile on his face. <quote>“The pony heard it, too,”</quote> he said. <quote>“She jumped as if she had been shot. If I had not grasped at the reins—for I was frightened, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>—”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“No shame to you, my boy,”</quote> said I, though I scarcely knew why.</p>

<p tone="suspenseful"><quote>“If I hadn’t held to her like a leech, she’d have pitched me over her head, and never drew breath till we were at the door. Did the pony dream it?”</quote> he said, with a soft disdain, yet indulgence for my foolishness. Then he added slowly, <quote>“It was only a cry the first time, and all the time before you went away. I wouldn’t tell you, for it was so wretched to be frightened. I thought it might be a hare or a rabbit snared, and I went in the morning and looked; but there was nothing. It was after you went I heard it really first; and this is what he says.”</quote> He raised himself on his elbow close to me, and looked me in the face: <quote>“‘Oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in! oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in!’”</quote> As he said the words a mist came over his face, the mouth quivered, the soft features all melted and changed, and when he had ended these pitiful words, dissolved in a shower of heavy tears.
    </p>
    <p tone="fear">
<quote>“This is very touching, <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>,”</quote> I said.</p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Oh, if you had just heard it, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>! I said to myself, if <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character> heard it he would do something; but mamma, you know, she’s given over to <character ref="Simson">Simson</character>, and that fellow’s a <character ref="Simson">doctor</character>, and never thinks of anything but clapping you into bed.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“We must not blame <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> for being a <character ref="Simson">doctor</character>, <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>.”</quote></p>

<p tone="happiness"><quote>“No, no,”</quote> said my boy, with delightful toleration and indulgence; <quote>“oh, no; that’s the good of him; that’s what he’s for; I know that. But you—you are different; you are just <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>; and you’ll do something—directly, <character ref="Mortimer">papa</character>, directly; this very night.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Surely,”</quote> I said. <quote>“No doubt it is some little lost child.”</quote></p>

<p tone="suspenseful">He gave me a sudden, swift look, investigating my face as though to see whether, after all, this was everything my eminence as <quote>“<character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>”</quote> came to,—no more than that. Then he got hold of my shoulder, clutching it with his thin hand. <quote>“Look here,”</quote> he said, with a quiver in his voice; <quote>“suppose it wasn’t—living at all!”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“My dear boy, how then could you have heard it?”</quote> I said.</p>

<p tone="cynical">He turned away from me with a pettish exclamation,—<quote>“As if you didn’t know better than that!”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Do you want to tell me it is a ghost?”</quote> I said.</p>

<p tone="serious"><character ref="Roland">Roland</character> withdrew his hand; his countenance assumed an aspect of great dignity and gravity; a slight quiver remained about his lips. <quote>“Whatever it was—you always said we were not to call names. It was something—in trouble. Oh, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>, in terrible trouble!”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“But, my boy,”</quote> I said (I was at my wits’ end), <quote>“if it was a child that was lost, or any poor human creature—but, <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, what do you want me to do?”</quote></p>

<p tone="sadness"><quote>“I should know if I was you,”</quote> said the child eagerly. <quote>“That is what I always said to myself,—<character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character> will know. Oh, <character ref="Mortimer">papa</character>, <character ref="Mortimer">papa</character>, to have to face it night after night, in such terrible, terrible trouble, and never to be able to do it any good! I don’t want to cry; it’s like a baby, I know; but what can I do else? Out there all by itself in the ruin, and nobody to help it! I can’t bear it! I can’t bear it!”</quote> cried my generous boy. And in his weakness he burst out, after many attempts to restrain it, into a great childish fit of sobbing and tears.
    </p>
    <p tone="sadness">
<quote>“It will be there now!—it will be there all the night! Oh, think, <character ref="Mortimer">papa</character>,—think if it was me! I can’t rest for thinking of it. Don’t!”</quote> he cried, putting away my hand,—<quote>“don’t! You go and help it, and <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> can take care of me.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“But, <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, what can I do?”</quote></p>

<p tone="optimism">My boy opened his eyes, which were large with weakness and fever, and gave me a smile such, I think, as sick children only know the secret of. <quote>“I was sure you would know as soon as you came. I always said, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character> will know. And <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>,”</quote> he cried, with a softening of repose upon his face, his limbs relaxing, his form sinking with a luxurious ease in his bed,—<quote>“<character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> can come and take care of me.”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
It was then I remembered suddenly the looks of the men when they turned to take the brougham to <place>the stables</place> in the dark that morning. They had not liked it, and the horses had not liked it. I remembered that even in my anxiety about <character ref="Roland">Roland</character> I had heard them tearing along the avenue back to <place>the stables</place>, and had made a memorandum mentally that I must speak of it. It seemed to me that the best thing I could do was to go to <place>the stables</place> now and make a few inquiries. It is impossible to fathom the minds of rustics; there might be some devilry of practical joking, for anything I knew; or they might have some interest in getting up a bad reputation for the <place>Brentwood</place> avenue. It was getting dark by the time I went out, and nobody who knows the country will need to be told how black is the darkness of a November night under high laurel-bushes and yew-trees. I walked into the heart of the shrubberies two or three times, not seeing a step before me, till I came out upon the broader carriage-road, where the trees opened a little, and there was a faint gray glimmer of sky visible, under which the great limes and elms stood darkling like ghosts; but it grew black again as I approached the corner where the ruins lay. Both eyes and ears were on the alert, as may be supposed; but I could see nothing in the absolute gloom, and, so far as I can recollect, I heard nothing. Nevertheless there came a strong impression upon me that somebody was there. It is a sensation which most people have felt. I have seen when it has been strong enough to awake me out of sleep, the sense of some one looking at me. I suppose my imagination had been affected by <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>’s story; and the mystery of the darkness is always full of suggestions. I stamped my feet violently on the gravel to rouse myself, and called out sharply, <quote>“Who’s there?”</quote> Nobody answered, nor did I expect any one to answer, but the impression had been made. I was so foolish that I did not like to look back, but went sideways, keeping an eye on the gloom behind. It was with great relief that I spied the light in <place>the stables</place>, making a sort of oasis in the darkness. I walked very quickly into the midst of that lighted and cheerful place, and thought the clank of the groom’s pail one of the pleasantest sounds I had ever heard. The <character ref="Jarvis">coachman</character> was the head of this little colony, and it was to his house I went to pursue my investigations. He was a native of the district, and had taken care of the place in the absence of the family for years; it was impossible but that he must know everything that was going on, and all the traditions of the place. The men, I could see, eyed me anxiously when I thus appeared at such an hour among them, and followed me with their eyes to Jarvis’s house, where he lived alone with his old wife, their children being all married and out in the world. <character ref="Mrs. Jarvis">Mrs. Jarvis</character> met me with anxious questions. How was the poor young gentleman? But the others knew, I could see by their faces, that not even this was the foremost thing in my mind.</p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Noises?—ou ay, there’ll be noises,—the wind in the trees, and the water soughing down <place>the glen</place>. As for tramps, Cornel, no, there’s little o’ that kind o’ cattle about here; and Merran at the gate’s a careful body.”</quote> <character ref="Jarvis">Jarvis</character>moved about with some embarrassment from one leg to another as he spoke. He kept in the shade, and did not look at me more than he could help. Evidently his mind was perturbed, and he had reasons for keeping his own counsel. His wife sat by, giving him a quick look now and then, but saying nothing. The kitchen was very snug and warm and bright,—as different as could be from the chill and mystery of the night outside.</p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“I think you are trifling with me, Jarvis,”</quote> I said.</p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Triflin’, Cornel? No me. What would I trifle for? If the deevil himsel was in the <place>auld hoose</place>, I have no interest in ’t one way or another—”</quote></p>

<p tone="anger"><quote>“Sandy, hold your peace!”</quote> cried his wife imperatively.</p>

<p tone="anger"><quote>“And what am I to hold my peace for, wi’ the Cornel standing there asking a’ thae questions? I’m saying, if the deevil himsel—”</quote></p>

<p tone="anger"><quote>“And I’m telling ye hold your peace!”</quote> cried the woman, in great excitement. <quote>“Dark November weather and lang nichts, and us that ken a’ we ken. How daur ye name—a name that shouldna be spoken?”</quote> She threw down her stocking and got up, also in great agitation. <quote>“I tellt ye you never could keep it. It’s no a thing that will hide, and the haill toun kens as weel as you or me. Tell the Cornel straight out—or see, I’ll do it. I dinna hold wi’ your secrets, and a secret that the haill toun kens!”</quote> She snapped her fingers with an air of large disdain. As for Jarvis, ruddy and big as he was, he shrank to nothing before this decided woman. He repeated to her two or three times her own adjuration, <quote>“Hold your peace!”</quote> then, suddenly changing his tone, cried out, <quote>“Tell him then, confound ye! I’ll wash my hands o’t. If a’ the ghosts in <place>Scotland</place> were in the <place>auld hoose</place>, is that ony concern o’ mine?”</quote></p>

<p tone="suspenseful">After this I elicited without much difficulty the whole story. In the opinion of the Jarvises, and of everybody about, the certainty that the place was haunted was beyond all doubt. As Sandy and his wife warmed to the tale, one tripping up another in their eagerness to tell everything, it gradually developed as distinct a superstition as I ever heard, and not without poetry and pathos. How long it was since <character ref="the voice">the voice</character> had been heard first, nobody could tell with certainty. Jarvis’s opinion was that his <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>, who had been <character ref="Jarvis">coachman</character> at <place>Brentwood</place> before him, had never heard anything about it, and that the whole thing had arisen within the last ten years, since the complete dismantling of the old house; which was a wonderfully modern date for a tale so well authenticated. According to these witnesses, and to several whom I questioned afterwards, and who were all in perfect agreement, it was only in the months of November and December that <quote>“the visitation”</quote> occurred. During these months, the darkest of the year, scarcely a night passed without the recurrence of these inexplicable cries. Nothing, it was said, had ever been seen,—at least, nothing that could be identified. Some people, bolder or more imaginative than the others, had seen the darkness moving, <character ref="Mrs. Jarvis">Mrs. Jarvis</character> said, with unconscious poetry. It began when night fell, and continued, at intervals, till day broke. Very often it was only all inarticulate cry and moaning, but sometimes the words which had taken possession of my poor boy’s fancy had been distinctly audible,—<quote>“Oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in!”</quote> The Jarvises were not aware that there had ever been any investigation into it. The estate of <place>Brentwood</place> had lapsed into the hands of a distant branch of the family, who had lived but little there; and of the many people who had taken it, as I had done, few had remained through two Decembers. And nobody had taken the trouble to make a very close examination into the facts. <quote>“No, no,”</quote> <character ref="Jarvis">Jarvis</character>said, shaking his head, <quote>“No, no, Cornel. Wha wad set themsels up for a laughin’-stock to a’ the country-side, making a wark about a ghost? Naebody believes in ghosts. It bid to be the wind in the trees, the last gentleman said, or some effec’ o’ the water wrastlin’ among the rocks. He said it was a’ quite easy explained; but he gave up the hoose. And when you cam, Cornel, we were awfu’ anxious you should never hear. What for should I have spoiled the bargain and hairmed the property for no-thing?”</quote></p>

<p tone="anger"><quote>“Do you call my child’s life nothing?”</quote> I said in the trouble of the moment, unable to restrain myself. <quote>“And instead of telling this all to me, you have told it to him,—to a delicate boy, a child unable to sift evidence or judge for himself, a tender-hearted young creature—”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="suspenseful">
<quote>“Cornel,”</quote> said <character ref="Jarvis">Jarvis</character>solemnly, <quote>“and she’ll bear me witness,—the young gentleman never heard a word from me—no, nor from either groom or gardener; I’ll gie ye my word for that. In the first place, he’s no a lad that invites ye to talk. There are some that are, and some that arena. Some will draw ye on, till ye’ve tellt them a’ the clatter of the toun, and a’ ye ken, and whiles mair. But Maister <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, his mind’s fu’ of his books. He’s aye civil and kind, and a fine lad; but no that sort. And ye see it’s for a’ our interest, Cornel, that you should stay at <place>Brentwood</place>. I took it upon me mysel to pass the word,—‘No a syllable to Maister <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, nor to the young leddies—no a syllable.’ The women-servants, that have little reason to be out at night, ken little or nothing about it. And some think it grand to have a <character ref="the voice">ghost</character>so long as they’re no in the way of coming across it. If you had been tellt the story to begin with, maybe ye would have thought so yourself.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious">This was true enough, though it did not throw any light upon my perplexity. If we had heard of it to start with, it is possible that all the family would have considered the possession of a <character ref="the voice">ghost</character>a distinct advantage. It is the fashion of the times. We never think what a risk it is to play with young imaginations, but cry out, in the fashionable jargon, <quote>“A ghost!—nothing else was wanted to make it perfect.”</quote> I should not have been above this myself. I should have smiled, of course, at the idea of the <character ref="the voice">ghost</character>at all, but then to feel that it was mine would have pleased my vanity. Oh, yes, I claim no exemption. The girls would have been delighted. I could fancy their eagerness, their interest, and excitement. No; if we had been told, it would have done no good,—we should have made the bargain all the more eagerly, the fools that we are. <quote>“And there has been no attempt to investigate it,”</quote> I said, <quote>“to see what it really is?”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Eh, Cornel,”</quote> said the <character ref="Jarvis">coachman</character>’s wife, <quote>“wha would investigate, as ye call it, a thing that nobody believes in? Ye would be the laughin’-stock of a’ the country-side, as my man says.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“But you believe in it,”</quote> I said, turning upon her hastily. The woman was taken by surprise. She made a step backward out of my way.</p>

<p tone="fear"><quote>“Lord, Cornel, how ye frichten a body! Me!—there’s awfu’ strange things in this world. An unlearned person doesna ken what to think. But the <character ref="Moncrieff">Moncrieff</character> and the gentry they just laugh in your face. Inquire into the thing that is not! Na, na, we just let it be.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Come with me, Jarvis,”</quote> I said hastily, <quote>“and we’ll make an attempt at least. Say nothing to the men or to anybody. I’ll come back after dinner, and we’ll make a serious attempt to see what it is, if it is anything. If I hear it,—which I doubt,—you may be sure I shall never rest till I make it out. Be ready for me about ten o’clock.”</quote></p>

<p tone="fear"><quote>“Me, Cornel!”</quote> <character ref="Jarvis">Jarvis</character>said, in a faint voice. I had not been looking at him in my own preoccupation, but when I did so, I found that the greatest change had come over the fat and ruddy <character ref="Jarvis">coachman</character>. <quote>“Me, Cornel!”</quote> he repeated, wiping the perspiration from his brow. His ruddy face hung in flabby folds, his knees knocked together, his voice seemed half extinguished in his throat. Then he began to rub his hands and smile upon me in a deprecating, imbecile way. <quote>“There’s nothing I wouldna do to pleasure ye, Cornel,”</quote> taking a step further back. <quote>“I’m sure she kens I’ve aye said I never had to do with a mair fair, weel-spoken gentleman—”</quote> Here <character ref="Jarvis">Jarvis</character>came to a pause, again looking at me, rubbing his hands.</p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Well?”</quote> I said.</p>

<p tone="fear"><quote>“But eh, sir!”</quote> he went on, with the same imbecile yet insinuating smile, <quote>“if ye’ll reflect that I am no used to my feet. With a horse atween my legs, or the reins in my hand, I’m maybe nae worse than other men; but on fit, Cornel—It’s no the—bogles—but I’ve been cavalry, ye see,”</quote> with a little hoarse laugh, <quote>“a’ my life. To face a thing ye dinna understan’—on your feet, Cornel.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Well, sir, if I do it,”</quote> said I tartly, <quote>“why shouldn’t you?”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Eh, Cornel, there’s an awfu’ difference. In the first place, ye tramp about the haill countryside, and think naething of it; but a walk tires me mair than a hunard miles’ drive; and then ye’re a gentleman, and do your ain pleasure; and you’re no so auld as me; and it’s for your ain bairn, ye see, Cornel; and then—”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“He believes in it, Cornel, and you dinna believe in it,”</quote> the woman said.</p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Will you come with me?”</quote> I said, turning to her.</p>

<p tone="fear">She jumped back, upsetting her chair in her bewilderment. <quote>“Me!”</quote> with a scream, and then fell into a sort of hysterical laugh. <quote>“I wouldna say but what I would go; but what would the folk say to hear of <character ref="Cornel Mortimer">Cornel Mortimer</character> with an auld silly woman at his heels?”</quote></p>

<p tone="n/a">The suggestion made me laugh too, though I had little inclination for it. <quote>“I’m sorry you have so little spirit, Jarvis,”</quote> I said. <quote>“I must find some one else, I suppose.”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
And it will be thought very strange, but it would be weak not to add, that I myself, though bent on the investigation I have spoken of, pledged to <character ref="Roland">Roland</character> to carry it out, and feeling that my boy’s health, perhaps his life, depended on the result of my inquiry,—I felt the most unaccountable reluctance to pass these ruins on my way home. My curiosity was intense; and yet it was all my mind could do to pull my body along. I daresay the scientific people would describe it the other way, and attribute my cowardice to the state of my stomach. I went on; but if I had followed my impulse, I should have turned and bolted. Everything in me seemed to cry out against it: my heart thumped, my pulses all began, like sledge-hammers, beating against my ears and every sensitive part. It was very dark, as I have said; the old house, with its shapeless tower, loomed a heavy mass through the darkness, which was only not entirely so solid as itself. On the other hand, the great dark cedars of which we were so proud seemed to fill up the night. My foot strayed out of the path in my confusion and the gloom together, and I brought myself up with a cry as I felt myself knock against something solid. What was it? The contact with hard stone and lime and prickly bramble-bushes restored me a little to myself. <quote>“Oh, it’s only the old gable,”</quote> I said aloud, with a little laugh to reassure myself. The rough feeling of the stones reconciled me. As I groped about thus, I shook off my visionary folly. What so easily explained as that I should have strayed from the path in the darkness? This brought me back to common existence, as if I had been shaken by a wise hand out of all the silliness of superstition. How silly it was, after all! What did it matter which path I took? I laughed again, this time with better heart, when suddenly, in a moment, the blood was chilled in my veins, a shiver stole along my spine, my faculties seemed to forsake me. Close by me, at my side, at my feet, there was a sigh. No, not a groan, not a moaning, not anything so tangible,—a perfectly soft, faint, inarticulate sigh. I sprang back, and my heart stopped beating. Mistaken! no, mistake was impossible. I heard it as clearly as I hear myself speak; a long, soft, weary sigh, as if drawn to the utmost, and emptying out a load of sadness that filled the breast. To hear this in the solitude, in the dark, in the night (though it was still early), had an effect which I cannot describe. I feel it now,—something cold creeping over me, up into my hair, and down to my feet, which refused to move. I cried out, with a trembling voice, <quote>“Who is there?”</quote> as I had done before; but there was no reply.</p>

<p tone="n/a">I got home I don’t quite know how; but in my mind there was no longer any indifference as to the thing, whatever it was, that haunted these ruins. My scepticism disappeared like a mist. I was as firmly determined that there was something as <character ref="Roland">Roland</character> was. I did not for a moment pretend to myself that it was possible I could be deceived; there were movements and noises which I understood all about,—cracklings of small branches in the frost, and little rolls of gravel on the path, such as have a very eerie sound sometimes, and perplex you with wonder as to who has done it, when there is no real mystery; but I assure you all these little movements of nature don’t affect you one bit when there is something. I understood them. I did not understand the sigh. That was not simple nature; there was meaning in it, feeling, the soul of a creature invisible. This is the thing that human nature trembles at,—a creature invisible, yet with sensations, feelings, a power somehow of expressing itself. I had not the same sense of unwillingness to turn my back upon the scene of the mystery which I had experienced in going to <place>the stables</place>; but I almost ran home, impelled by eagerness to get everything done that had to be done, in order to apply myself to finding it out. <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character> was in the hall as usual when I went in. He was always there in the afternoon, always with the appearance of perfect occupation, yet, so far as I know, never doing anything. The door was open, so that I hurried in without any pause, breathless; but the sight of his calm regard, as he came to help me off with my overcoat, subdued me in a moment. Anything out of the way, anything incomprehensible, faded to nothing in the presence of <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character>. You saw and wondered how he was made: the parting of his hair, the tie of his white neckcloth, the fit of his trousers, all perfect as works of art; but you could see how they were done, which makes all the difference. I flung myself upon him, so to speak, without waiting to note the extreme unlikeness of the man to anything of the kind I meant. <quote>“<character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character>,”</quote> I said, <quote>“I want you to come out with me to-night to watch for—”</quote></p>

<p tone="n/a"><quote>“Poachers, Colonel?”</quote> he said, a gleam of pleasure running all over him.</p>

<p tone="n/a"><quote>“No, <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character>; a great deal worse,”</quote> I cried.</p>

<p tone="n/a"><quote>“Yes, Colonel; at what hour, sir?”</quote> the man said; but then I had not told him what it was.
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
We went, so far as I could guess, exactly as I had come; when I heard that sigh. The darkness, however, was so complete that all marks, as of trees or paths, disappeared. One moment we felt our feet on the gravel, another sinking noiselessly into the slippery grass, that was all. I had shut up my lantern, not wishing to scare any one, whoever it might be. <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character> followed, it seemed to me, exactly in my footsteps as I made my way, as I supposed, towards the mass of the ruined house. We seemed to take a long time groping along seeking this; the squash of the wet soil under our feet was the only thing that marked our progress. After a while I stood still to see, or rather feel, where we were. The darkness was very still, but no stiller than is usual in a winter’s night. The sounds I have mentioned—the crackling of twigs, the roll of a pebble, the sound of some rustle in the dead leaves, or creeping creature on the grass—were audible when you listened, all mysterious enough when your mind is disengaged, but to me cheering now as signs of the livingness of nature, even in the death of the frost. As we stood still there came up from the trees in <place>the glen</place> the prolonged hoot of an owl. <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character> started with alarm, being in a state of general nervousness, and not knowing what he was afraid of. But to me the sound was encouraging and pleasant, being so comprehensible.</p>

<p tone="suspenseful"><quote>“An owl,”</quote> I said, under my breath. <quote>“Y—es, Colonel,”</quote> said <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character>, his teeth chattering. We stood still about five minutes, while it broke into the still brooding of the air, the sound widening out in circles, dying upon the darkness. This sound, which is not a cheerful one, made me almost gay. It was natural, and relieved the tension of the mind. I moved on with new courage, my nervous excitement calming down.
    </p>
    <p tone="fear">
I went myself to the other side of the wall, keeping close to it. The light shook in <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character>’s hand, but, tremulous though it was, shone out through <place>the vacant door</place>, one oblong block of light marking all the crumbling corners and hanging masses of foliage. Was that something dark huddled in a heap by the side of it? I pushed forward across the light in the door-way, and fell upon it with my hands; but it was only a juniper-bush growing close against the wall. Meanwhile, the sight of my figure crossing the door-way had brought <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character>’s nervous excitement to a height: he flew at me, gripping my shoulder. <quote>“I’ve got him, Colonel! I’ve got him!”</quote> he cried, with a voice of sudden exultation. He thought it was a man, and was at once relieved. But at that moment <character ref="the voice">the voice</character> burst forth again between us, at our feet,—more close to us than any separate being could be. He dropped off from me, and fell against the wall, his jaw dropping as if he were dying. I suppose, at the same moment, he saw that it was me whom he had clutched. I, for my part, had scarcely more command of myself. I snatched the light out of his hand, and flashed it all about me wildly. Nothing,—the juniper-bush which I thought I had never seen before, the heavy growth of the glistening ivy, the brambles waving. It was close to my ears now, crying, crying, pleading as if for life. Either I heard the same words <character ref="Roland">Roland</character> had heard, or else, in my excitement, his imagination got possession of mine. <character ref="the voice">The voice</character> went on, growing into distinct articulation, but wavering about, now from one point, now from another, as if the owner of it were moving slowly back and forward. <quote>“<character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">Mother</character>! <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>!”</quote> and then an outburst of wailing. As my mind steadied, getting accustomed (as one’s mind gets accustomed to anything), it seemed to me as if some uneasy, miserable creature was pacing up and down before a closed door. Sometimes—but that must have been excitement—I thought I heard a sound like knocking, and then another burst, <quote>“Oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>! <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>!”</quote> All this close, close to the space where I was standing with my lantern, now before me, now behind me: a creature restless, unhappy, moaning, crying, before <place>the vacant door</place>-way, which no one could either shut or open more.</p>

<p tone="fear"><quote>“Do you hear it, <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character>? do you hear what it is saying?”</quote> I cried, stepping in through the door-way. He was lying against the wall, his eyes glazed, half dead with terror. He made a motion of his lips as if to answer me, but no sounds came; then lifted his hand with a curious imperative movement as if ordering me to be silent and listen. And how long I did so I cannot tell. It began to have an interest, an exciting hold upon me, which I could not describe. It seemed to call up visibly a scene any one could understand,—a something shut out, restlessly wandering to and fro; sometimes <character ref="the voice">the voice</character> dropped, as if throwing itself down, sometimes wandered off a few paces, growing sharp and clear. <quote>“Oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in! oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in! oh, let me in!”</quote> Every word was clear to me. No wonder the boy had gone wild with pity. I tried to steady my mind upon <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, upon his conviction that I could do something, but my head swam with the excitement, even when I partially overcame the terror. At last the words died away, and there was a sound of sobs and moaning. I cried out, <quote>“In the name of God, who are you?”</quote> with a kind of feeling in my mind that to use the name of God was profane, seeing that I did not believe in ghosts or anything supernatural; but I did it all the same, and waited, my heart giving a leap of terror lest there should be a reply. Why this should have been I cannot tell, but I had a feeling that if there was an answer it would be more than I could bear. But there was no answer; the moaning went on, and then, as if it had been real, <character ref="the voice">the voice</character> rose a little higher again, the words recommenced, <quote>“Oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in! oh, <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>, let me in!”</quote> with an expression that was heart-breaking to hear.
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
<quote>“You’ve got an epidemic in your house, Colonel,”</quote> <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> said to me next morning. <quote>“What’s the meaning of it all? Here’s your <character ref="Bagley">butler</character> raving about a voice. This will never do, you know; and so far as I can make out, you are in it too.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Yes, I am in it, <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>. I thought I had better speak to you. Of course you are treating <character ref="Roland">Roland</character> all right, but the boy is not raving, he is as sane as you or me. It’s all true.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“As sane as—I—or you. I never thought the boy insane. He’s got cerebral excitement, fever. I don’t know what you’ve got. There’s something very queer about the look of your eyes.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Come,”</quote> said I, <quote>“you can’t put us all to bed, you know. You had better listen and hear the symptoms in full.”</quote></p>

<p tone="cynical">The <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character> shrugged his shoulders, but he listened to me patiently. He did not believe a word of the story, that was clear; but he heard it all from beginning to end. <quote>“My dear fellow,”</quote> he said, <quote>“the boy told me just the same. It’s an epidemic. When one person falls a victim to this sort of thing, it’s as safe as can be,—there’s always two or three.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Then how do you account for it?”</quote> I said.</p>

<p tone="cynical"><quote>“Oh, account for it!—that’s a different matter; there’s no accounting for the freaks our brains are subject to. If it’s delusion, if it’s some trick of the echoes or the winds,—some phonetic disturbance or other—”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Come with me to-night, and judge for yourself,”</quote> I said.</p>

<p tone="cynical">Upon this he laughed aloud, then said, <quote>“That’s not such a bad idea; but it would ruin me forever if it were known that <character ref="John">John</character> <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> was ghost-hunting.”</quote></p>

<p tone="cynical"><quote>“There it is,”</quote> said I; <quote>“you dart down on us who are unlearned with your phonetic disturbances, but you daren’t examine what the thing really is for fear of being laughed at. That’s science!”</quote></p>

<p tone="cynical"><quote>“It’s not science,—it’s common-sense,”</quote> said the <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>. <quote>“The thing has delusion on the front of it. It is encouraging an unwholesome tendency even to examine. What good could come of it? Even if I am convinced, I shouldn’t believe.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“I should have said so yesterday; and I don’t want you to be convinced or to believe,”</quote> said I. <quote>“If you prove it to be a delusion, I shall be very much obliged to you for one. Come; somebody must go with me.”</quote></p>

<p tone="cynical"><quote>“You are cool,”</quote> said the <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>. <quote>“You’ve disabled this poor fellow of yours, and made him—on that point—a lunatic for life; and now you want to disable me. But, for once, I’ll do it. To save appearance, if you’ll give me a bed, I’ll come over after my last rounds.”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
That night at eleven I met <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> at the gate. He had come by train, and I let him in gently myself. I had been so much absorbed in the coming experiment that I passed the ruins in going to meet him, almost without thought, if you can understand that. I had my lantern; and he showed me a coil of taper which he had ready for use. <quote>“There is nothing like light,”</quote> he said, in his scoffing tone. It was a very still night, scarcely a sound, but not so dark. We could keep the path without difficulty as we went along. As we approached the spot we could hear a low moaning, broken occasionally by a bitter cry. <quote>“Perhaps that is your voice,”</quote> said the <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>; <quote>“I thought it must be something of the kind. That’s a poor brute caught in some of these infernal traps of yours; you’ll find it among the bushes somewhere.”</quote> I said nothing. I felt no particular fear, but a triumphant satisfaction in what was to follow. I led him to the spot where <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character> and I had stood on the previous night. All was silent as a winter night could be,—so silent that we heard far off the sound of the horses in <place>the stables</place>, the shutting of a window at the house. <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> lighted his taper and went peering about, poking into all the corners. We looked like two conspirators lying in wait for some unfortunate traveller; but not a sound broke the quiet. The moaning had stopped before we came up; a star or two shone over us in the sky, looking down as if surprised at our strange proceedings. <character ref="Dr. Simson">Dr. Simson</character> did nothing but utter subdued laughs under his breath. <quote>“I thought as much,”</quote> he said. <quote>“It is just the same with tables and all other kinds of ghostly apparatus; a sceptic’s presence stops everything. When I am present nothing ever comes off. How long do you think it will be necessary to stay here? Oh, I don’t complain; only when you are satisfied, I am—quite.”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
We walked home very silent afterwards. It was only when we were in sight of the house that I said, <quote>“What do you think of it?”</quote> <quote>“I can’t tell what to think of it,”</quote> he said quickly. He took—though he was a very temperate man—not the claret I was going to offer him, but some brandy from the tray, and swallowed it almost undiluted. <quote>“Mind you, I don’t believe a word of it,”</quote> he said, when he had lighted his candle; <quote>“but I can’t tell what to think,”</quote> he turned round to add, when he was half-way upstairs.
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
Next morning <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> was out before breakfast, and came in with evident signs of the damp grass on his boots, and a look of worry and weariness, which did not say much for the night he had passed. He improved a little after breakfast, and visited his two patients,—for <character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character> was still an invalid. I went out with him on his way to the train, to hear what he had to say about the boy. <quote>“He is going on very well,”</quote> he said; <quote>“there are no complications as yet. But mind you, that’s not a boy to be trifled with, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>. Not a word to him about last night.”</quote> I had to tell him then of my last interview with <character ref="Roland">Roland</character>, and of the impossible demand he had made upon me, by which, though he tried to laugh, he was much discomposed, as I could see. <quote>“We must just perjure ourselves all round,”</quote> he said, <quote>“and swear you exorcised it;”</quote> but the man was too kind-hearted to be satisfied with that. <quote>“It’s frightfully serious for you, <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>. I can’t laugh as I should like to. I wish I saw a way out of it, for your sake. By the way,”</quote> he added shortly, <quote>“didn’t you notice that juniper-bush on the left-hand side?”</quote> <quote>“There was one on the right hand of the door. I noticed you made that mistake last night.”</quote> <quote>“Mistake!”</quote> he cried, with a curious low laugh, pulling up the collar of his coat as though he felt the cold,—<quote>“there’s no juniper there this morning, left or right. Just go and see.”</quote> As he stepped into the train a few minutes after, he looked back upon me and beckoned me for a parting word. <quote>“I’m coming back to-night,”</quote> he said.
    </p>
    <p tone="happiness">
<quote>“Come away, Colonel <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>,”</quote> he said; <quote>“I’m all the more glad to see you, that I feel it’s a good sign for the boy. He’s doing well?—God be praised,—and the Lord bless him and keep him. He has many a poor body’s prayers, and that can do nobody harm.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“He will need them all, <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character>,”</quote> I said, <quote>“and your counsel too.”</quote> And I told him the story,—more than I had told <character ref="Simson">Simson</character>. The old clergyman listened to me with many suppressed exclamations, and at the end the water stood in his eyes.</p>

<p tone="optimism"><quote>“That’s just beautiful,”</quote> he said. <quote>“I do not mind to have heard anything like it; it’s as fine as Burns when he wished deliverance to one—that is prayed for in no kirk. Ay, ay! so he would have you console the poor lost spirit? God bless the boy! There’s something more than common in that, Colonel <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>. And also the faith of him in his <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character>!—I would like to put that into a sermon.”</quote> Then the old gentleman gave me an alarmed look, and said, <quote>“No, no; I was not meaning a sermon; but I must write it down for the ‘Children’s Record.’”</quote> I saw the thought that passed through his mind. Either he thought, or he feared I would think, of a funeral sermon. You may believe this did not make me more cheerful.</p>

<p tone="serious">I can scarcely say that <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> gave me any advice. How could any one advise on such a subject? But he said, <quote>“I think I’ll come too. I’m an old man; I’m less liable to be frightened than those that are further off the world unseen. It behooves me to think of my own journey there. I’ve no cut-and-dry beliefs on the subject. I’ll come too; and maybe at the moment the Lord will put into our heads what to do.”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
The road to the station and the <place>village</place> lay through <place>the glen</place>, not by the ruins; but though the sunshine and the fresh air, and the beauty of the trees, and the sound of the water were all very soothing to the spirits, my mind was so full of my own subject that I could not refrain from turning to the right hand as I got to the top of <place>the glen</place>, and going straight to the place which I may call the scene of all my thoughts. It was lying full in the sunshine, like all the rest of the world. The ruined gable looked due east, and in the present aspect of the sun the light streamed down through the door-way as our lantern had done, throwing a flood of light upon the damp grass beyond. There was a strange suggestion in the open door,—so futile, a kind of emblem of vanity: all free around, so that you could go where you pleased, and yet that semblance of an enclosure,—that way of entrance, unnecessary, leading to nothing. And why any creature should pray and weep to get in—to nothing, or be kept out—by nothing, you could not dwell upon it, or it made your brain go round. I remembered, however, what <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> said about the juniper, with a little smile on my own mind as to the inaccuracy of recollection which even a scientific man will be guilty of. I could see now the light of my lantern gleaming upon the wet glistening surface of the spiky leaves at the right hand,—and he ready to go to the stake for it that it was the left! I went round to make sure. And then I saw what he had said. Right or left there was no juniper at all! I was confounded by this, though it was entirely a matter of detail nothing at all,—a bush of brambles waving, the grass growing up to the very walls. But after all, though it gave me a shock for a moment, what did that matter? There were marks as if a number of footsteps had been up and down in front of the door, but these might have been our steps; and all was bright and peaceful and still. I poked about the other ruin—the larger ruins of the old house—for some time, as I had done before. There were marks upon the grass here and there—I could not call them footsteps—all about; but that told for nothing one way or another. I had examined the ruined rooms closely the first day. They were half filled up with soil and debris, withered brackens and bramble,—no refuge for any one there. It vexed me that <character ref="Jarvis">Jarvis</character>should see me coming from that spot when he came up to me for his orders. I don’t know whether my nocturnal expeditions had got wind among the servants, but there was a significant look in his face. Something in it I felt was like my own sensation when <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> in the midst of his scepticism was struck dumb. <character ref="Jarvis">Jarvis</character>felt satisfied that his veracity had been put beyond question. I never spoke to a servant of mine in such a peremptory tone before. I sent him away <quote>“with a flea in his lug,”</quote> as the man described it afterwards. Interference of any kind was intolerable to me at such a moment.
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
<character ref="Simson">Simson</character> came out to dinner, and when the house was all still, and most of the servants in bed, we went out and met <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character>, as we had appointed, at the head of <place>the glen</place>. <character ref="Simson">Simson</character>, for his part, was disposed to scoff at the <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>. <quote>“If there are to be any spells, you know, I’ll cut the whole concern,”</quote> he said. I did not make him any reply. I had not invited him; he could go or come as he pleased. He was very talkative, far more so than suited my humor, as we went on. <quote>“One thing is certain, you know; there must be some human agency,”</quote> he said. <quote>“It is all bosh about apparitions. I never have investigated the laws of sound to any great extent, and there’s a great deal in ventriloquism that we don’t know much about.”</quote> <quote>“If it’s the same to you,”</quote> I said, <quote>“I wish you’d keep all that to yourself, <character ref="Simson">Simson</character>. It doesn’t suit my state of mind.”</quote> <quote>“Oh, I hope I know how to respect idiosyncrasy,”</quote> he said. The very tone of his voice irritated me beyond measure. These scientific fellows, I wonder people put up with them as they do, when you have no mind for their cold-blooded confidence. <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> met us about eleven o’clock, the same time as on the previous night. He was a large man, with a venerable countenance and white hair,—old, but in full vigor, and thinking less of a cold night walk than many a younger man. He had his lantern, as I had. We were fully provided with means of lighting the place, and we were all of us resolute men. We had a rapid consultation as we went up, and the result was that we divided to different posts. <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> remained inside the wall—if you can call that inside where there was no wall but one. <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> placed himself on the side next the ruins, so as to intercept any communication with the old house, which was what his mind was fixed upon. I was posted on the other side. To say that nothing could come near without being seen was self-evident. It had been so also on the previous night. Now, with our three lights in the midst of the darkness, the whole place seemed illuminated. <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character>’s lantern, which was a large one, without any means of shutting up,—an old-fashioned lantern with a pierced and ornamental top,—shone steadily, the rays shooting out of it upward into the gloom. He placed it on the grass, where the middle of the room, if this had been a room, would have been. The usual effect of the light streaming out of the door-way was prevented by the illumination which <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> and I on either side supplied. With these differences, everything seemed as on the previous night.
    </p>
    <p tone="suspenseful">
We were all perfectly still till the first outburst was exhausted, as I knew, by experience, it would be. <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character>, to whom it was new, was quite motionless on the other side of the wall, as we were in our places. My heart had remained almost at its usual beating during <character ref="the voice">the voice</character>. I was used to it; it did not rouse all my pulses as it did at first. But just as it threw itself sobbing at the door (I cannot use other words), there suddenly came something which sent the blood coursing through my veins, and my heart into my mouth. It was a voice inside the wall,—the <character ref="Moncrieff">Moncrieff</character>’s well-known voice. I would have been prepared for it in any kind of adjuration, but I was not prepared for what I heard. It came out with a sort of stammering, as if too much moved for utterance. <quote>“<character ref="Willie">Willie</character>, <character ref="Willie">Willie</character>! Oh, God preserve us! is it you?”</quote></p>

<p tone="sadness">These simple words had an effect upon me that <character ref="the voice">the voice</character> of the invisible creature had ceased to have. I thought the old man, whom I had brought into this danger, had gone mad with terror. I made a dash round to the other side of the wall, half crazed myself with the thought. He was standing where I had left him, his shadow thrown vague and large upon the grass by the lantern which stood at his feet. I lifted my own light to see his face as I rushed forward. He was very pale, his eyes wet and glistening, his mouth quivering with parted lips. He neither saw nor heard me. We that had gone through this experience before, had crouched towards each other to get a little strength to bear it. But he was not even aware that I was there. His whole being seemed absorbed in anxiety and tenderness. He held out his hands, which trembled, but it seemed to me with eagerness, not fear. He went on speaking all the time. <quote>“<character ref="Willie">Willie</character>, if it is you,—and it’s you, if it is not a delusion of Satan,—<character ref="Willie">Willie</character>, lad! why come ye here frighting them that know you not? Why came ye not to me?”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious">He seemed to wait for an answer. When his voice ceased, his countenance, every line moving, continued to speak. <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> gave me another terrible shock, stealing into the open door-way with his light, as much awe-stricken, as wildly curious, as I. But the <character ref="Moncrieff">Moncrieff</character> resumed, without seeing <character ref="Simson">Simson</character>, speaking to some one else. His voice took a tone of expostulation:—</p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Is this right to come here? Your <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>’s gone with your name on her lips. Do you think she would ever close her door on her own lad? Do ye think the Lord will close the door, ye faint-hearted creature? No!—I forbid ye! I forbid ye!”</quote> cried the old man. The sobbing voice had begun to resume its cries. He made a step forward, calling out the last words in a voice of command. <quote>“I forbid ye! Cry out no more to man. Go home, ye wandering spirit! go home! Do you hear me?—me that christened ye, that have struggled with ye, that have wrestled for ye with the Lord!”</quote> Here the loud tones of his voice sank into tenderness. <quote>“And her too, poor woman! poor woman! her you are calling upon. She’s not here. You’ll find her with the Lord. Go there and seek her, not here. Do you hear me, lad? go after her there. He’ll let you in, though it’s late. Man, take heart! if you will lie and sob and greet, let it be at heaven’s gate, and not your poor <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character>’s ruined door.”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
<quote>“Lord,”</quote> the <character ref="Moncrieff">Moncrieff</character> said,—<quote>“Lord, take him into Thy everlasting habitations. The <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> he cries to is with Thee. Who can open to him but Thee? Lord, when is it too late for Thee, or what is too hard for Thee? Lord, let that woman there draw him inower! Let her draw him inower!”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="sadness">
It seemed to me that it must be the middle of the night, as we all walked back. It was in reality very late. <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> put his arm into mine. He walked slowly, with an air of exhaustion. It was as if we were coming from a death-bed. Something hushed and solemnized the very air. There was that sense of relief in it which there always is at the end of a death-struggle. And nature, persistent, never daunted, came back in all of us, as we returned into the ways of life. We said nothing to each other, indeed, for a time; but when we got clear of the trees and reached the opening near the house, where we could see the sky, <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> himself was the first to speak. <quote>“I must be going,”</quote> he said; <quote>“it’s very late, I’m afraid. I will go down <place>the glen</place>, as I came.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“But not alone. I am going with you, <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Well, I will not oppose it. I am an old man, and agitation wearies more than work. Yes; I’ll be thankful of your arm. To-night, Colonel, you’ve done me more good turns than one.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious">I pressed his hand on my arm, not feeling able to speak. But <character ref="Simson">Simson</character>, who turned with us, and who had gone along all this time with his taper flaring, in entire unconsciousness, came to himself, apparently at the sound of our voices, and put out that wild little torch with a quick movement, as if of shame. <quote>“Let me carry your lantern,”</quote> he said; <quote>“it is heavy.”</quote> He recovered with a spring; and in a moment, from the awe-stricken spectator he had been, became himself, sceptical and cynical. <quote>“I should like to ask you a question,”</quote> he said. <quote>“Do you believe in Purgatory, <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>? It’s not in the tenets of the Church, so far as I know.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“Sir,”</quote> said <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character>, <quote>“an old man like me is sometimes not very sure what he believes. There is just one thing I am certain of—and that is the loving-kindness of God.”</quote></p>

<p tone="cynical"><quote>“But I thought that was in this life. I am no theologian—”</quote></p>

<p tone="optimism"><quote>“Sir,”</quote> said the old man again, with a tremor in him which I could feel going over all his frame, <quote>“if I saw a friend of mine within the gates of hell, I would not despair but his <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character> would take him by the hand still, if he cried like you.”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious"><quote>“I allow it is very strange, very strange. I cannot see through it. That there must be human agency, I feel sure. <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character>, what made you decide upon the person and the name?”</quote></p>

<p tone="serious">The <character ref="Moncrieff">Moncrieff</character> put out his hand with the impatience which a man might show if he were asked how he recognized his brother. <quote>“Tuts!”</quote> he said, in familiar speech; then more solemnly, <quote>“How should I not recognize a person that I know better—far better—than I know you?”</quote></p>

<p tone="suspenseful"><quote>“Then you saw the man?”</quote>
    </p>
    <p tone="optimism">
<quote>“Far from that—better. God bless him!”</quote> <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> said.
    </p>
    <p tone="serious">
For some nights after, I watched among the ruins, spending all the dark hours up to midnight patrolling about the bit of wall which was associated with so many emotions; but I heard nothing, and saw nothing beyond the quiet course of nature; nor, so far as I am aware, has anything been heard again. <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> gave me the history of the youth, whom he never hesitated to name. I did not ask, as <character ref="Simson">Simson</character> did, how he recognized him. He had been a prodigal,—weak, foolish, easily imposed upon, and <quote>“led away,”</quote> as people say. All that we had heard had passed actually in life, the <character ref="Simson">Doctor</character> said. The young man had come home thus a day or two after his <character ref="Mrs. Mortimer">mother</character> died,—who was no more than the housekeeper in the old house,—and distracted with the news, had thrown himself down at the door and called upon her to let him in. The old man could scarcely speak of it for tears. To me it seemed as if—Heaven help us, how little do we know about anything!—a scene like that might impress itself somehow upon the hidden heart of nature. I do not pretend to know how, but the repetition had struck me at the time as, in its terrible strangeness and incomprehensibility, almost mechanical,—as if the unseen actor could not exceed or vary, but was bound to re-enact the whole. One thing that struck me, however, greatly, was the likeness between the old <character ref="Moncrieff">Moncrieff</character> and my boy in the manner of regarding these strange phenomena. <character ref="Dr. Moncrieff">Dr. Moncrieff</character> was not terrified, as I had been myself, and all the rest of us. It was no <quote>“ghost,”</quote> as I fear we all vulgarly considered it, to him,—but a poor creature whom he knew under these conditions, just as he had known him in the flesh, having no doubt of his identity. And to <character ref="Roland">Roland</character> it was the same. This spirit in pain,—if it was a spirit,—this voice out of the unseen,—was a poor fellow-creature in misery, to be succored and helped out of his trouble, to my boy. He spoke to me quite frankly about it when he got better. <quote>“I knew <character ref="Mortimer">Mortimer</character> would find out some way,”</quote> he said. And this was when he was strong and well, and all idea that he would turn hysterical or become a seer of visions had happily passed away.
    </p>
    <p tone="happiness">
<character ref="Bagley">Bagley</character> left my service as soon as he got well. He assured me it was no want of respect, but he could not stand <quote>“them kind of things;”</quote> and the man was so shaken and ghastly that I was glad to give him a present and let him go. For my own part, I made a point of staying out the time—two years—for which I had taken <place>Brentwood</place>; but I did not renew my tenancy. By that time we had settled, and found for ourselves a pleasant home of our own.</p>
</chapter>
</story>